בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is כ"ו Chaf Vav בבא
מציעא Bava Metzia 26. We pick up at the top line and
our learning should be in the זכות zechut of the protection of
our חיילים hayalim and חיילות hayalot and the swift return of all
the hostages and the speedy end of the war. Okay, so we're
continuing with the משנה Mishna and the משנה Mishna said that if
you found a מציאה metzia under rubble or in an old wall
that you can keep it and the גמרא Gemara said that the
case was that it was very rusted, so you assume that it
was left there by even the previous inhabitants of the land and
it's definitely ייאוש ye'ush and therefore you can keep it. Now if
you find it however in a new wall, it says and that's
the part we're now going to focus on, if it's on the
half of the wall facing רשות הרבים reshut harabim you can keep
it because it was left there by one of the people of
רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, and if it's facing on the inside of
the wall towards a person's private domain then it belongs to that
person, you have to assume that the person put it there and
you can't keep it. רש"י Rashi of course points out that even
if it's on the part facing the רשות הרבים reshut harabim presumably
it was left there by one of the people of רשות הרבים,
reshut harabim, it's not an אבידה aveda at all, it's a case
of הינוח, hinuach, something that's been intentionally left, but because the גמרא
Gemara has said that the case of the משנה Mishna is that
the thing is rusted over, so therefore even if it was at
one point הינוח hinuach by now we can assume it's been forgotten
about and abandoned and therefore you can keep it. But if it
always belonged to the owner then it still is the owner's and
it is never considered and it never has the status of אבידה;
aveda; it was his and it's in his property, even if he
forgot about it it's not an אבידה. aveda. Okay, so let's take
a look top of כ"ו עמוד א'. Chaf Vav Amud Aleph. בכותל
חדש מחציו ולחוץ שלו מחציו ולפנים של בעל הבית, Bechotel chadash mechetzi
ulachutz shelo mechetzi ulifnim sheba'al habayit, the half facing the outside towards
רשות הרבים reshut harabim you can keep it, מחציו ולפנים של בעל
הבית mechetzi ulifnim sheba'al habayit the half facing inwards to the person's
private domain it belongs to the owner of the house. אמר רב
אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, סכינא בתר קתא, sakina batar kata, if it's
a knife it goes by the handle. So obviously you would put
in a knife you would be holding on to the handle, so
even if the blade of the knife is facing the רשות הרבים
reshut harabim half, if the handle is facing the person's private domain
you assume it was put in by the person in the private
domain and the same in the reverse.
וכיסא בתר שנסיה vechisa batar shinsei
and a like a wallet, a you know a pouch goes by
the straps. So you would put it in with the straps facing
you, so therefore based on where the straps are is whether you
decide whether it was put in by somebody from the public domain
or whether it was put in by the house owner by the
homeowner. ואלא מתניתין דקתני מחציו ולחוץ שלו מחציו ולפנים של בעל הבית
ולחזי אי קתא לגאו אי קתא לבר אי שנסיה לגאו אי שנסיה
לבר? v'ela matnitin de-katani me-chetzi u-lachutz shelo me-chetzi u-lifnim she-ba'al ha-bayit, ve-lechze
ikata le-gav ikata le-var, i-shinsei le-gav i-shinsei le-var?
So the משנה mishna that says you look at whether it's on
the outer half or the inner half, why not just look where's
the handle? Is it on the inside or the outside?
Where are the straps on the inside or the outside? So the
answer is obvious because that only applies to two cases. So the
גמרא Gemara says מתניתין באודרא ונסכא. matnitin be-udra ve-naska. No,
our משנה mishna is talking about like you're
dealing with like rags or metal strips and therefore you know anything
other than a knife or a or a pouch anything that you
know that it's not indicated which way it went in. תנא, Tana,
now we're talking about a ברייתא, braitah, אם היה כותל ממולא בהן,
im haya kotel memule bahen, if the hole of the wall was
filled,
so it's both on the inside, you know it's both on the
inner half and the outer half, it fills the entire hole, so
which where do you assume it came from the inside or the
outside?
חולקין, cholkin,
so you divide. The part on the outside you assume came from
רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, the part on the inside you assume came
from the owner. Now that seems a little arbitrary because obviously it
seems like it's all one and it either came from the owner
or from the רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, but if you can't decide
then you split it down the middle and you can keep the
part facing out and not the part facing in. פשיטא, peshita, obvious.
Now I don't know if it's so obvious but okay. So the
גמרא Gemara says לא צריכא דמשופא בחד גיסא, lo tzericha de-mishupa bechad
gisa,
it's angled in one direction, so you know it's all like inclined
with a downward slope towards let's say the רשות הרבים. reshut harabim.
מהו דתימא אישתפוכי אישתפוך קמשמע לן, mah de-teima ishtapuche ishtapach, k'mashma lan,
I might think so I will assume that it all started on
the side of the בעל הבית ba'al habayit and then it just
rolled down because it's inclined or the reverse. So it says you
don't assume that if it's right now situated and it totally fills
from one end to the other then you conceptually you split it
again, which I think is a big חידוש chidush because clearly it
either came from one side or the other, but since we can't
decide which we split it down the middle and the part on
the outside you can keep and the part on the inside you
leave and you assume it belongs to the בעל הבית. ba'al habayit.
All right now the גמרא Gemara continues, אם היה משכירה לאחרים אפילו
בתוך הבית הרי. im haya maskira la-acherim afilu betoch habayit hare. אם
היה משכיר לאחרים אפילו בתוך הבית הרי אלו שלו. Im haya maskir
l'acheirim afilu b'toch habayis harei eilu shelo. If the house was rented
to others, then even if you found something in the house and
you you can keep it. Now you, you're not the owner and
you're not a renter. I don't know what you were, you're let's
say I don't know the cleaning person that you were sent into
the house to clean it and you found that somebody left behind
some coins or something and this was a rental property, then you
can keep it because you don't know which person left it since
it's regularly rented out. Even the last person who was there, you
know, maybe it wasn't them, maybe it was the person before them,
so you have no idea. There's no סימן. siman. Let's assume we're
talking without a סימן, siman, and and there's no reason in particular
to assume that it belongs to the landlord. Now an interesting point
here is, okay, but you're the cleaning person and you found it,
but if it's an אבידה aveidah and it's no סימן siman and
it belongs to the person who finds it, why shouldn't the landlord
own it? It's in his property. Why shouldn't the fact that it's
in his property essentially claim it for him? So תוספות Tosfos asks
this question and תוספות Tosfos basically says from here you see that
you cannot say that your property can be קונה koneh something for
you if it's something that, you know, you wouldn't be aware of.
And even though we normally say, you know, that your חצר chatzer
is קונה koneh שלא מדעתו shelo m'da'ato etc., it would not apply
if it's a מציאה metzia that you, the owner, would not be
aware of. All right, so that's an important concept here. All right,
so now let's take a look.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues like this. And by the
way תוספות Tosfos also says if you look at the תוספות בתוך
הבית הרי אלו שלו, Tosfos b'toch habayis harei eilu shelo, מהו שמצא
בזה ענין שנודע שהוא אבידה, mahu shematza b'ze inyan shenoda shehu aveidah,
it's clear that it was lost there. It wasn't just some object
of the owner's that you happened to find inside some dresser drawer
or something like that. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara continues
like this.
We say... it says the following... but before we continue, let's just
look at that previous תוספות דשייך. Tosfos d'shayeich. תוספות Tosfos says the
following, ואם תאמר, V'im tomar, this is actually going on the previous
גמרא Gemara about something in the ancient wall, but it's the same
relevance here. ולקני ליה חצר לבעל הגל או לבעל הכותל, V'likni lei
chatzer l'baal hagal o l'baal hakosel, why don't you own it? It's
in your property. Why does it go to the person who finds
it? ויש לומר דאין חצר קונה בדבר שיכול להיות שלא ימצאנו לעולם
כמו הכא שהוא מוטמן בעובי הכותל. V'yesh lomar d'ein chatzer koneh b'davar
sheyachol lihyos shelo yimtza'enu l'olam k'mo hacha shehu mutman b'ovi hakosel.
Okay, so if it's something even if it's on your property, if
it's something that you might never find, we don't say that your
חצר chatzer is קונה. koneh. It has to be an אבידה, aveidah,
has to be found in order to then be taken possession of,
and this is not yet found. Okay, so that's why when you're
cleaning, you can keep it. So let's see now what the גמרא
Gemara says. Okay, so it says like this. It says באמאי? ליזל
בתר בתרא. B'amai? Leizil basar basra.
Why do you say well we don't know who lost it and
therefore it's just in a case of like an אבידה aveidah without
a סימן siman and I'll keep it? Why don't you assume that
it came from the last renter? Shouldn't we assume if you found,
I don't know, twenty dollars in the corner of the room that
was rented out, the guy who last rented out the room was
the one who dropped it? Where do we know this principle? מי
לא תנן, Mi lo snan, did we not teach in a משנה?
mishna? מעות שנמצאו לפני סוחרי בהמה. Maos shenimtzu lifnei socharei beheima. If
you're in ירושלים Yerushalayim and you find money that is in front
of the people who sell animals, לעולם מעשר. L'olam maaser. You always
consider it to be מעשר, maaser, meaning whether it's during the time
of the רגל regel or not during the time of the רגל,
regel, you always consider this to be מעשר. maaser. Why? Because when
people when you bring your מעשר maaser money to ירושלים Yerushalayim and
your מעשר maaser money has to be used to eat in ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, your מעשר שני maaser sheni money, and therefore people would bring
it at a whole range of times and therefore the majority of
people buying animals from the people selling animals for slaughter in ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, the majority of the money there would be מעשר maaser money
at all times of the year. All right, now תוספות Tosfos says
how do you know maybe that it didn't fall, you know, after
it was purchased? You know, maybe it fell from the from the
from the owner, and once the animal is purchased, the sanctity goes
off the money. But תוספות Tosfos says nevertheless because the like large
majority of the number of people are the purchasers, not the sellers,
and so therefore we would go by them and we would say
it fell from them, not that it fell from the seller. All
right, so therefore, money the majority of people buy buying animals for
for slaughter in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, it's מעשר שני maaser sheni money, and
if you find money there at any time of the year, you
assume that it's מעשר שני maaser sheni money. Okay, that's not relevant
for us yet. Okay, but that's that's point number one. בהר הבית
חולין. Behar habayis chullin.
So if it is on the Temple Mount mount, you assume that
it is unsanctified money.
Why? Because, well let's take a look at the next line. ובירושלים,
U'v'yerushalayim, now if it's in ירושלים Yerushalayim but it's not in front
of people that are selling
animals, בשאר ימות השנה חולין. B'shaar yemos hashana chullin. Okay, the majority
of money in ירושלים Yerushalayim in, you know, when it's not right
there right in front of the butchers, the majority of the money
is חולין chullin at at all time the normal times of the
year, so you would assume that the money you found is חולין.
chullin. However, בשעת הרגל הכל מעשר. B'shas haregel hakol maaser. At the
time of the רגל, regel, הכל מעשר. hakol maaser. that's when there's
tons of people there, and again, everybody who's coming up for the
רגל Regel is using it as an opportunity to spend their מעשר
Ma'aser money, מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheini money in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So during
the רגל, Regel, you assume that all the money is מעשר שני
Ma'aser Sheini money or the majority of it is wherever you find
it in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. The question is, why is it different on
הר הבית Har HaBayit than in ירושלים? Yerushalayim? Why by ירושלים Yerushalayim
do you go by the time of the year, and by הר
הבית Har HaBayit even at, you know, at the רגל, Regel, do
you assume that it is חולין? Chullin? So let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says. So the גמרא Gemara says, ואמר רב שמעיה בר
זעירא, Ve'amar Rav Shemaya Bar Zeira, מאי טעמא, Mai Ta'ama,
what's the reason by ירושלים Yerushalayim you go by what the current
time of year is? הואיל ושוקי ירושלים עשויים להתכבד בכל יום. Ho'il
v'shukei Yerushalayim asuyim l'hitkabed b'chol yom. Because they would sweep the streets
in ירושלים Yerushalayim every single day. And therefore, if the money was
dropped from before, even if now it's the רגל, Regel, maybe this
money was dropped last week? Why do we assume the money that
was found was dropped right now? Because they sweep the streets daily,
and if the money had been dropped earlier, it would have been
found when it was swept through. So any money you found now,
we say was dropped now. That's why in ירושלים Yerushalayim you go
by the time of year. Whereas on הר הבית, Har HaBayit, they
would not sweep it regularly. Why not? רש"י Rashi says for two
reasons. Number one, it was a mountain, so it was sloped, so
the wind would sort of take care of that, you know, it
wouldn't get all the coins obviously, but you wouldn't need a regular
sweeping. But money therefore could be left from before. And number two,
you're not supposed to go onto הר הבית Har HaBayit when you're
dusty. So there would be less of a need to sweep הר
הבית. Har HaBayit. So on הר הבית Har HaBayit even during the
רגל, Regel, you say, you don't know, did the coin fall now?
Did it fall last week? Did it fall last month? So you
look at the, you don't look at the immediate time, you look
at the big picture and most of the money, you know, over
time is not מעשר. Ma'aser. That's on הר הבית. Har HaBayit. But
in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, because it's swept daily, you say anything that was
found was found now, and you
know, if it was dropped yesterday, it would have been found yesterday.
And that's why you can assume that in the רגל Regel time,
it's מעשר שני, Ma'aser Sheini, the rest of the time it's חולין.
Chullin. So what does that show you? That shows you that you
say that you go by the last person if you could assume
that it was cleaned out from before. So therefore here too you
would say the same thing. As רש"י Rashi says, you know, if
you're renting out an apartment, before you leave a hotel room, what
do you do? You know, you search around and you look under
the bed and you make sure you haven't left anything. So it's
just like the שוקי ירושלים, Shukei Yerushalayim, marketplaces of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So
therefore you assume that the person, you know, people clean it out
before they go. So if you find twenty-dollar bills when you're cleaning
a hotel room, so obviously somebody missed it, but you assume it's
the last person that missed it, right? If it was dropped earlier,
then the guy before the last person, you know, he would have
found it or the person coming after him would have found it.
So therefore that's like שוקי ירושלים Shukei Yerushalayim because before one person
leaves they always clean it out. So anything that's found, you assume
it comes by the most recent person. That's a pretty reasonable question.
So even if it's a hotel room and you're the cleaning crew
and you found it, why not assume it came from the last
person? So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
Okay, הכא נמי, Hacha nami, here too say קמא קמא אזול, kama
kama azul, any money that was dropped from the previous person has
gone, you know, has been cleaned away, it was already found when
they left, והני בתראו, ve'hani batrayu, and this twenty dollars that you
found in the corner that was from the last person. So אמר
ריש לקיש Amar Reish Lakish says ריש לקיש Reish Lakish משום בר
קפרא mishum Bar Kappara in the name of בר קפרא, Bar Kappara,
כגון שעשו פונדק לשלושה ישראל kegon she'asu pundak l'shlosha Yisrael or לשלושה
בני אדם. l'shlosha bnei adam.
The case is is that you rented it out to actually three
people. It was not just rented out to one person. And since
it was rented out to three people at the same time, you
don't know who dropped it. In this case, could still be a
case where there's no סימן. siman. There's no סימן, siman, it's a
classic case of something with no סימן siman and you know, you
don't know who dropped it, so you can keep it. But the
גמרא Gemara is going to understand that once we said that it
fell from three people, we could be talking even if it's something
with a סימן. siman. Let's take a look. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this, שמע מינה, Shema mina, should we infer from
this הלכה כרבי שמעון בן אלעזר halacha k'Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar אפילו
ברוב ישראל afilu b'rov Yisrael that we rule like רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar
that says that if it was something was dropped in a place
where there was masses, you know, even with a סימן siman you
would not have to return it, the owners would be מיאש miya'esh
because they would assume that, you know, like if you dropped something
in the middle of Time Square, technically you have a סימן, siman,
but there's so many people there you assume that somebody is going
to take it and not return it. So and the גמרא Gemara
sort of that was the position of רבי שמעון בן אלעזר, Rabbi
Shimon ben Elazar, there was a question whether he said that just
by a majority non-Jews or majority Jews. So the גמרא Gemara now
is assuming a couple of things and it's a strange גמרא. Gemara.
Because number one, רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar only
said his place like במקום שהרבים מצויין, bimkom sheharabim m'tzuyin, in a
place where there's tons of people, not any place where there was
like just, you know, like a few people. A few people, that's
a normal case. You lost an object. If you lost it in
a park and there was ten people in the park, you know,
that would be a classic case where you would return a מציאה.
metziah. So it's a little bizarre that the גמרא Gemara thinks that
this is relevant to רבי שמעון בן אלעזר. Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar.
רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar was only talking about
מקום שהרבים מצויים, makom sheharabbim metzuyim,
but somehow the גמרא Gemara sort of assumes we're talking with a
סימן siman and the reason now you don't have to return it
is because there are three people and that shows like רבי שמעון
בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar that if there's a רבים rabbim
even if they're Jews you don't have to return it. Okay, and
the fact that there were three people becomes like a מקום שהרבים
מצויים. makom sheharabbim metzuyim. So again, a little strange that the גמרא
Gemara went in that direction. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara answers.
אלא, Ella, so would that show you that רבי שמעון בן אלעזר
Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar that this is going like רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar and the reason you don't return it
because now we're assuming it has a סימן siman is because you
go by if it's רבים מצויים rabbim metzuyim even by רוב ישראל?
rov Yisrael? אלא אמר רב מנשיא בר יעקב כגון שעשאו פונדק לשלושה
עובדי כוכבים. Ella amar Rav Menashia bar Yaakov kegon sheasao pundak lishlosha
ovdei kochavim. Fine,
we're not talking about Jews. You lent, you rented it out to
three non-Jews and therefore you don't have to return it. Of course,
if it's non-Jews, then you know, it's a little funny then even
if it's one non-Jew and he's the last one and you go,
you know, you don't have to return a מציאה metziah to a
non-Jew according to the עיקר הלכה. ikar halacha. So it becomes very
strange. That's not the point of the משנה. Mishna. The משנה Mishna
has to do with the fact that it's regularly rented out and
now the גמרא Gemara made it about the fact that it was
non-Jews. Very strange. The easier answer is what it said before. You
rented it out to a few people, they're Jews, it's not מקום
שהרבים מצויים, makom sheharabbim metzuyim, but it's also not a place where
it has a סימן siman since you don't know who it came
from, there are different rentees, so therefore, and they were all at
the same time, therefore you do not have to return. Okay, anyway,
but this is the way the גמרא Gemara is explaining it, that
it was non-Jews. רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה אפילו תימא לשלושה
ישראל. Rav Nachman amar Rabba bar Abua afilu teima lishlosha Yisrael. Even
if it were three Jews. מאי טעמא ההוא דנפל מיניה מייאש. Mai
taama hahu denafal minei miyaiesh. The guy who dropped it, he's מייאש.
miyaiesh. Why is he מייאש? miyaiesh? מימר אמר מכדי, Meimar amar michdi,
meaning he's מייאש miyaiesh even if רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon
ben Elazar would say that when there's normally רבים מצויים rabbim metzuyim
in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael there's no יאוש yeush if it's a
סימן. siman. Here there would be יאוש yeush even with a סימן.
siman. Why? Because here it's not just generic masses. If it's a
general place where there's a lot of Jews, you'll figure I've got
a סימן, siman, somebody will find it and return it. But here
you were renting this with two other people and presumably you were
looking around for it as you were all moving out of the
room. Hey, did anybody find my wallet? And everybody said no, no,
I didn't find it, I didn't find it. So at that stage,
you don't expect that you're going to get it back. As opposed
to if you lost it, you know, in the middle of Central
Park, you figure somebody will find it with a סימן, siman, they'll
contact me. But here you asked the people that should know and
they said no. So that's what the גמרא Gemara says: ההוא דנפל
מיניה מייאש, Hahu denafal minei miyaiesh, you're מייאש. miyaiesh. מימר אמר, Meimar
amar, you say מכדי אינש אחרינא לא הוי בהדי אלא הני, michdi
inish achrina lo hava behadi ella hanei,
nobody else was around, the only people in this room were these
other two guys. אמרי קמייהו כמה זימני להדרו לי, Amri kammaihu kamma
zimni lehadru li, I said to them a few times, guys, do
you have my wallet, have you seen it, give it back to
me. ולא הדרו לי, Velo hadru li, and they didn't give it
back to me. והשתא להדרו, Vehashta lehadru, all of a sudden now
they're going to return it? So you know, if you lost your
wallet and it's not in Central Park, there maybe with a סימן
siman you'll think you'll get it back. But here in the room,
there's only two other people and they both said they didn't see
it, they both said they didn't get it back, so you figure
that's it, I can't find it, they said they didn't have it,
probably one of them stole it or it's nowhere to be found.
That's it, I'm מייאש. miyaiesh. Okay, and so in that case there
would be יאוש yeush with three people even with a סימן. siman.
Okay. אי דאית להו להדורי
אהדרו ניהלי, Ei deit lehu lehadorei ahadru nihali, if they were planning
on returning it, they would have returned it to me. והאי דלא
אהדרו לי בדעתייהו למיגזליה, Vehai dela ahadru li bedataihu lemigzaleih, and the
reason they didn't return it to me, they must be planning on
stealing it. All right, so that's we've gone pretty much far from
our משנה. Mishna. Our משנה Mishna just sounds like it's a room
that's regularly rented out, high turnover, you have no idea who it
came from, you can keep it. But because of the גמרא's Gemara
question that you should go by the last person, we say a
special case that we're talking about that it was rented out to
three people and we assume יאוש yeush because the person who lost
it, since the other two guys didn't fess up, that person is
definitely מייאש. miyaiesh. All right, now the גמרא Gemara says like this,
ואזל רב נחמן לטעמיה. Veazal Rav Nachman letaameih. Now this רב נחמן
Rav Nachman idea that like you say, since they know and they
didn't give it back, they would know, they didn't give it back
to me, that's it, I'm מייאש, miyaiesh, he's following his other reasoning.
דאמר רב נחמן, Damar Rav Nachman, because רב נחמן Rav Nachman said,
ראה סלע שנפל משניים, Raah sela shenafal mishnayim,
if you saw two people that they, you know, were sitting down
and they got up and they dropped a coin. חייב להחזיר, Chayav
lehachazir, you have to return it to them. מאי טעמא, Mai taama,
ההוא דנפל מיניה לא מייאש, Hahu denafal minei lo miyaiesh, the guy
who dropped it isn't מייאש. miyaiesh. Why not? Even when he realizes
that he dropped it. רש"י Rashi starts introducing the whole question of
אביי ורבא Abaye veRava and יאוש שלא מדעת. yeush shelo madaat. But
remember the גמרא Gemara said before that you are always checking your
pocket. So you saw them drop it. Even if you then run
over to get it, you can assume that by that time the
person has, you know, checked his pocket and realized that he's lost
it, and nevertheless no יאוש. yeush. Why no יאוש? yeush? לא מייאש.
Lo miyaiesh. מימר אמר מכדי אינך אחריני לא הוו בהדאי אלא האי.
Meimar amar michdei inach achrini lo havu behadai ella hai.
So there was only one other person. We were there, we were
sitting down, we got up, we walked a few minutes and I
realized I was missing my wallet. So I figured there's only one
person who might know where this wallet is, the guy who's with
me. אלא האי, Ella hai, נקטנא ליה, naktina leh, I'll take hold
of him, ואמינא ליה, ve'amina leh, אנת הוא דשקלתיה, at hu deshaktilah,
and I'll say you're the one who took it. So in that
case, it's funny, like if you had dropped your wallet in רשות
הרבים, reshus harabbim, so you would, you know, or let's say not
your wallet, let's say there's no סימן. siman. Okay, if you had
dropped $20 in רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, so you would say, okay,
that's it, I'm מייאש, miyayeish, you would find out, you would realize
right away and because people are always checking your pocket, and you
would be מייאש miyayeish right away. But in this case where you
were with your friend in רשות הרבים reshus harabbim and you got
up and you walked, or maybe you went to רשות הרבים, reshus
harabbim, wherever you were, and then you realized you were missing it,
you assume your friend is the one that either knows about it
or has it, and therefore you're not מייאש. miyayeish. All right, so
that's an interesting idea. But this is רב נחמן Rav Nachman going
to his reasoning that
that you're thinking about the people with you and that is structuring
the way you're thinking about whether you have ייאוש yei'ush or not
ייאוש, yei'ush, and it's different than if you had just realized you
were lost it and you were all alone and there were some
masses of people that might find it or not find it. So
in this scenario, two people, you're not going to have ייאוש, yei'ush,
even though normally you got up and you realized you were missing
your $20 you would have ייאוש. yei'ush. And now we're going to
get to a case where you're going to have ייאוש yei'ush like
a case of the three people moving out of the apartment.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, בשלושה bishlosha אינו חייב
להחזיר. eino chayav lehachazir.
However, if it were three people and they, you know, and they
were, you know, sitting in a place and then they got up
and they moved and then one guy realized, you know, that he
had dropped 20 bucks and you saw him drop the 20 bucks,
you don't have to give it back. Why? Because you can assume
that there is ייאוש. yei'ush. Why can you assume there is ייאוש?
yei'ush? מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? האי דנפל מיניה ודאי מייאש. hai dinfal
minei vadai miyayeish. The guy who dropped it is definitely מייאש. miyayeish.
מימר אמר מכדי, meimar amar michdei, תרי הוו בהדאי, trei havu behadai,
there were two people with me, אי נקטנא להאי, ei naktina lehai,
אמר לא שקלתיה, amar lo shaktilah, ואדנקטנא להאי, ve'ad naktina lehai, אמר
לא שקלתיה. amar lo shaktilah.
I'm never going to get it back, anyone I will take it
will say, hey, it wasn't me, maybe go ask the other guy.
The other guy says it wasn't me, go ask the other guy.
So in that case where you can, you know, where you don't
feel the belief that there's one person that you can demand it
from, you feel, ach, that's it, one of these two guys stole
it and I'm never going to get it back, they're just going
to claim somebody else took it. Okay, so that's parallel with two
people, one other person you think you will get it back, two
other people you think you won't get it back. Again, it's not
exactly the same because in this case we might be talking like
it doesn't have a סימן, siman, you know, whereas in our... or
maybe who knows, maybe it does, maybe it doesn't. Anyway, in our
case, you know, it was a case where
even if it had a סימן siman and you normally would have
expected you would have gotten it back, once there are two people
with you in the room you assume one of them has it
and
you assume you're never going to be able to get it back.
If there's one person you assume he does have it, you will
be able to get it back and there's no ייאוש. yei'ush. All
right. So now the גמרא Gemara continues like this. אמר רבא, Amar
Rava, said רבא, Rava, האי דאמרת בשלושה אינו חייב
להחזיר, hai de'amrat bishlosha eino chayav lehachazir,
that that you said that if there are three you don't have
to give it back, לא אמרן אלא דלית ביה שוה פרוטה לכל
חד וחד. lo amran ella deleis beih shaveh perutah lechol chad vechad.
That's only
if it's less than worth three פרוטות. perutos. If it's worth, you
know, anywhere up to 2.9 פרוטות, perutos, then you don't have to
give it back. אבל אית ביה שוה פרוטה לכל חד וחד, aval
is beih shaveh perutah lechol chad vechad, חייב להחזיר. chayav lehachazir. But
if it's worth three פרוטות perutos you have to give it back.
Why? מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the reason? אימר שותפי נינהו eimar
shutfei ninhu ולא מייאש. velo miyayeish. He says maybe they're all partners
and therefore it was owned by all of them and therefore there's
no ייאוש. yei'ush. So, meaning there's two things going on here. Number
one is, he says, the reason you're assuming ייאוש yei'ush is because
you assume each one is on their own. And therefore the guy
figures I lost it, I'll never get it back, anyone I accuse
will just point to the other one. If maybe they're all partners,
and if they were all partners in this, you know, they were
carrying some cash together as partners,
so then he would, you know, then there would be an assumption
that if, you know, if my partners have it, they're going to
give it back to me. There's some trust there, they're not going
to deny it to me. So so therefore, so רבא Rava says,
I don't agree with you. There's a possibility there's partners and there's
no ייאוש. yei'ush. But if it's worth less than three פרוטות, perutos,
I would agree with you, because then even if they are partners,
each one has less than a stake of a פרוטה. perutah. And
there's no obligation to return a מציאה metzia if it's worth less
than a פרוטה. perutah. And here... And here we see it means
less than a פרוטה pruta to each, to each person who owns
it. So in that case you wouldn't have to return it. But
as soon as it's worth three פרוטות, prutos, I don't agree with
you. Maybe they were partners and he's not afraid about not getting
it back. אמרי נשא Amri nassa some say, אמר רבא amar Rava
אף על גב דלית ביה אלא שוה שתי פרוטות af al gav
d'lais beih ella shoveh shtei prutos חייב להחזיר. chayav l'hachzir.
Really it doesn't have to be worth three פרוטות, prutos, it's enough
that it's worth two פרוטות. prutos. מאי טעמא? mai taama? אימא שותפין
נינהו eima shutfin ninhu וחד מינייהו אחולי אחליה למנתי גבי חברי. v'chad
mineihu achulei achleih l'mansei gabei chavrei.
Because maybe I'll say all three of them were שותפין shutfin
and one of them said, you know what, you guys keep
it, I don't want my part anymore. So therefore there would still
be a חיוב chiyuv to return it even if it's worth two
פרוטות prutos because each one of them have a stake of a
פרוטה. pruta. So you know it's a little interesting that it doesn't,
it assumes that either they're all שותפים shutpim or none of them
are שותפים. shutpim. רש''י Rashi tells us to deal with the possibility
that maybe from the outset two were שותפים shutpim and not the
third, but we won't worry about that. So רבא's Rava saying like
this: you are saying if there's three because you can accuse one,
they'll point to the other person, there's definitely יאוש, yeush, I'm going
to say that wouldn't happen if they're
שותפים shutpim and
because of the possibility they're שותפים, shutpim, there might not be יאוש
yeush and you have to return it. However, that will only be
if it's worth a פרוטה pruta to each person. Less than that
you don't have to return, you don't have to return an אבידה
aveidah less than a פרוטה. pruta. Or maybe if only if it's
worth two פרוטות prutos because then there's still the scenario that three
of them were שותפים shutpim and one of them waived his rights.
And therefore because the other two remained שותפים, shutpim, you would have
to return it to them. Alright, so but maybe רבא Rava would
assume if both two waived their rights, you know, then it would
be back to the case of like nobody being שותף. shutaf. Alright,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: ואמר רבא, v'amar Rava,
now רבא Rava says like this. So that's the end of that
discussion about when there are definitely people around, two or three, that
changes the calculus of יאוש yeush with or without a סימן siman
because of your assumption that your friend has it or is lying
or is holding onto it, won't give it back to you, should
know it, etc. etc. Now we're going to get to a very
different point about a statement of רבא Rava about some general principles
about the מצות ואיסורין mitzvos v'issurin around אבידה. aveidah. אמר רבא, amar
Rava, רבא Rava said: ראה סלע שנפלה raah sela shenafala
if you see a somebody dropped a coin, נטלה לפני יאוש natala
lifnei yeush על מנת לגזלה al m'nas l'gozla now you picked it
up before יאוש, yeush, okay, because even, you know, could be a
case that it was in a, רבא Rava normally says יאוש שלא
מדעת הוי יאוש yeush shelo madaas havei yeush but let's say whatever,
it was in a wallet, it was, you know, with had your
ID, okay, you picked it up and you knew there was not
yet יאוש yeush and so and you picked it up with the
intent to steal it, that you're not going to return it. You
were planning on keeping it even though you still have a מצוה
mitzvah to return
it. עבר בכולהו avar b'chulhu and you transgress all the prohibitions. משום
לא תגזול mishum lo sigzol you're stealing. ומשום השב תשיבם u'mishum hashev
teshivem
you did not do the מצוה mitzvah of, you have a positive
מצוה mitzvah of השבת אבידה hashavas aveidah which you're not being מקיים.
m'kayem. So A you're not being מקיים m'kayem השבת אבידה. hashavas aveidah.
B because it's not יאוש yeush you don't own it and it's
somebody else's and you're holding onto it so you're over לא תגזול.
lo sigzol. And three: ומשום לא תוכל להתעלם u'mishum lo suchal l'hisalem
there's a לא תעשה lo saaseh by אבידה, aveidah, you can't hide
yourself from it. You have a positive obligation to return it and
a negative prohibition to not, you know, to not like renege or
to not like abandon your obligation to return it. So you transgress
all of those. ואף על גב דחזרה לאחר יאוש v'af al gav
d'chazra l'achar yeush מתנה בעלמא הוא דיהיב ליה. matana b'alma hu d'yahiv
leih.
Even now if you're going to return this object after יאוש, yeush,
you're only giving back a gift, ואיסורא דעבד
עבד v'issura d'avad avad and the transgression you transgressed you transgressed. Now
the ראשונים Rishonim say that this line here is actually added by
the גאונים, Geonim, it wasn't one of the original lines of רבא.
Rava. And they actually ask a question: what does this mean that
if you give it back after יאוש yeush it's meaningless, it's only
giving a gift? I mean you stole it, if you steal an
object you're מקיים m'kayem the מצוה mitzvah of השבת גזילה. hashavas gezeilah.
And maybe you're מקיים m'kayem the מצוה mitzvah of השבת אבידה. hashavas
aveidah. Initially you were transgressed, you planned on not returning it, but
now eventually you returned it. Why should you not be מקיים m'kayem
the מצוה mitzvah of השבת גזילה hashavas gezeilah and השבת אבידה? hashavas
aveidah? That's the question. So תוספות Tosafos says that you actually are.
If you look at תוספות, Tosafos, תוספות Tosafos says: מתנה בעלמא הוא
דיהיב ליה ואם תאמר והלא לאו דלא תגזול מקרי ניתק לעשה, matana
b'alma hu d'yahiv leih v'im tomar v'halo lav d'lo sigzol mikri nitak
l'asei, it's connected to the עשה asei of returning. אם כן כיון
דתקנת גזלה לא מקרי מתנה גם השב תשיבם למה לא תקיים? im
kein keivan d'taknas gezeila lo mikri matana gam hashev teshivem lama lo
tekayem? Why didn't you do the מצוה, mitzvah, okay, eventually you did
the מצוה? mitzvah? Maybe you transgressed it initially but eventually you did
the מצוה mitzvah of השבת אבידה hashavas aveidah and השבת גזילה. hashavas
gezeilah. So says ויש לומר דלא קאי אלא אלאו דלא תוכל להתעלם.
v'yeish lomar d'lo ka'i ella a'lav d'lo suchal l'hisalem. No, really what
it just means is that you did not
fix the prohibition of you cannot hide yourself from returning it. The
negative prohibition of not turning away from an אבידה aveidah you transgressed,
but ultimately the מצוה mitzvah of השבת אבידה hashavas aveidah and השבת
גזילה hashavas gezeilah you would have fulfilled. That's תוספות'ס Tosafos's answer. The
בעל המאור Baal HaMaor has a creative answer that after ייאוש yei'ush
if we פוסק pasken ייאוש yei'ush is קונה, koneh, then you can't
be מקיים m'kayeim the מצוה. mitzvah.
It's a far-out answer. רמב"ן Ramban has an extremely creative answer. רמב"ן
Ramban says that it's true that if this were just an אבידה
aveidah and you picked it up and you didn't plan on stealing
it, you picked up an אבידה aveidah and you planned on returning
it, and then the owners were מייאש. m'yaeish. You wouldn't be able
to be קונה koneh it, and you would return it after ייאוש
yei'ush and you'd be מקיים m'kayeim the מצוה mitzvah of השבת אבידה.
hashavas aveidah. That's the principle. You pick it up before ייאוש, yei'ush,
their ייאוש yei'ush doesn't help. But he says here's why their ייאוש
yei'ush doesn't help. Their ייאוש yei'ush doesn't help by אבידה aveidah because
when you pick it up on the intent to return it, you
become a שומר shomer on their behalf. And it is considered, you're
like a יד בעלים. yad be'alim. You picked up their object to
return it, you're now watching their object on their behalf, you're now
an extension of the owner. So that's why when the owner eventually
is מייאש m'yaeish it doesn't work, because really he doesn't realize that
the object is already back in his possession. So ייאוש yei'ush doesn't
work if it's not a lost object. That's a normal scenario why
ייאוש yei'ush doesn't work after you picked up the object on the
intent to return it. But when you picked it up on the
intent to steal it, then you are not operating to protect it
for the owner and it is not in the owner's domain. And
therefore when the owner is מייאש, m'yaeish, actually as an אבידה, aveidah,
it's now אבידה aveidah plus ייאוש, yei'ush, it's not in their domain,
even though you picked it up with a מצוה mitzvah of השבה,
hashava, that does not prevent the ייאוש yei'ush of the owner from
being meaningful since you are not watching it for them. And now
actually you are קונה koneh it as an אבידה, aveidah, and now
if you would return it you would not be מקיים m'kayeim the
מצוה mitzvah of השבת אבידה, hashavas aveidah, now it actually belongs to
you. All right, so that was very creative of the רמב"ן. Ramban.
Anyway, it's not the פשט. pshat. The פשט pshat is that even
if you return it later you are מקיים m'kayeim the מצוה mitzvah
of השבת אבידה. hashavas aveidah. But that's point number one: you pick
it up before ייאוש yei'ush with the intent of stealing it, you
transgress everything. All right, keep on going. נטל לפני ייאוש על מנת
להחזירה. natul lifnei yei'ush al m'nas l'hachzirah.
Now a classic case, you're a good guy: you picked it up
before ייאוש yei'ush and you planned on returning it, ולאחר ייאוש נתכוון
לגוזלה. ul'achar yei'ush niskayvein l'gozlah.
But then it stayed around in your possession and you decided you
know what, to heck with it, I'm just going to keep it,
I'm not going to return it. So what have you transgressed now?
So it says עובר משום השב תשיבם. over mishum hasheiv teshiveim.
You only transgress not returning an אבידה. aveidah. You don't transgress the
prohibition of גזילה gezeilah or of לא תוכל להתעלם. lo suchal l'hisalam.
Why not? You're stealing it. So רש"י Rashi makes it sound like
because it was already in your possession. You can't steal something once
you're already holding on to it. But תוספות Tosafos says that's clearly
not true. There's a principle that if you deny for example a
worker their wages, you're עובר over on לא תגזול, lo sigzol, even
though it's already in your possession. תוספות Tosafos says the key here
is that it's after ייאוש yei'ush you planned on stealing it. So
once it's in your possession and it's after
ייאוש yei'ush it is at that point so detached from the owner
that you're not עובר over on לא תגזול. lo sigzol. You're also
not עובר over on לא תוכל להתעלם lo suchal l'hisalam because your
initial picking up was with the intent of returning it. לא תוכל
להתעלם lo suchal l'hisalam means you walk by it and you don't
pick it up to return it. Here you did pick it up
to return it. So you're not עובר over on לא תוכל להתעלם,
lo suchal l'hisalam, you're not עובר over on לא תגזול lo sigzol
because you only planned on stealing it after ייאוש. yei'ush. Okay, but
you are עובר over on השב תשיבם. hasheiv teshiveim. You have a
מצוה mitzvah to return it which you're not doing. That's that case.
Third case: המתין לה עד שנתייאשו הבעלים. himtin lah ad shenisyayshu habalim.
So the owner dropped it and you waited, you saw it, you
could have picked it up and returned it to the owner before
ייאוש, yei'ush, but you waited until the owner said, oh my God,
I just dropped, I realized I just lost my wallet, oh forget
it, I'm never going to get it back, and you waited for
ייאוש yei'ush and then you picked it up. אינו עובר אלא משום
לא תוכל להתעלם בלבד. eino over ella mishum lo suchal l'hisalam bilvad.
So the one thing, so you're not עובר over on השב תשיבם
hasheiv teshiveim because if you didn't pick it up you don't yet
have a מצוה mitzvah to return it. You're not עובר over on
לא תגזול. lo sigzol. You didn't steal it. After ייאוש yei'ush you
were allowed to take it. What you transgressed is you did not
act on seeing it and picking it up and acting to return
it right away. So that, by you waiting till after ייאוש, yei'ush,
so the fact that you didn't act, that was the transgression of
לא תוכל להתעלם. lo suchal l'hisalam. Not to hide yourself from it,
not to abandon it. You abandoned your responsibility of picking it up
and returning it. All right, so that's very important: the principles of
the מצוה mitzvah of השב תשיבם hasheiv teshiveim and לא תוכל להתעלם
lo suchal l'hisalam and how How they play out when you pick
it up and when you initially pick it up to steal it,
initially pick it up to return it, change your mind, or you
wait, ways you could be עובר over one without being עובר over
on the other. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר
רבא, Amar Rava, האי מאן דחזי דנפל זוזי מחבריה. hai man dechazi
denafal zuzei mechavrei.
So if somebody saw that his friend dropped a, you know, a
dollar, בחולתא becholasa in the middle of the sand, you were on
the beach and he lost something, you know, he lost his wallet,
okay, he lost twenty dollars, or he lost, you know,
he lost his Apple Watch. ואשכחי ve'ashkechei okay
and and you found it, ושקלי, veshaklei, לא מחייב לאהדורי ליה. lo
mechayav l'ahadorei lei.
And now you don't have to, you don't have to return it
to him. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? הוא דנפל מיניה מייאש. hu denafal
minei mi'ayesh.
The guy as soon as he dropped it on the beach, he's
definitely מייאש. mi'ayesh. Now here's the חידוש. chiddush. אף על גב דחזי
דאייתי ארבלא וקא מרבל, af al gav dechazi de'ayiti arbala veka marbel,
even if you go ahead and you saw him that he came
back with a sieve and he was sifting out the sand to
try to find it. He came back with a metal detector, okay,
doesn't that show you he's not מייאש? mi'ayesh? No, מימר אמר כי
היכי דנפל מינאי דידי הכי נפל מאינש אחרינא ומשכחנא מידי. meimar amar
ki heichi denafal minai didi hachi nafal me'inash acharina umeshachana midi. No,
the guy feel, just cause he's coming back with a sieve or
with a metal detector, doesn't prove that he's assuming he's going to
find his thing. He's really upset he lost his thing, but what
he figures is, other people lose stuff on the beach as well.
I'll come with a metal detector, with a sieve, and if I
don't find mine, I'll find somebody else's and at least I'll make
up my loss. So that is a real חידוש chiddush that we
don't assume that that means he's to give, he has, that he's
still not מייאש, mi'ayesh, we're going to assume definitely יאוש, ye'ush, but
a hope that he will find something else. Okay, we will end
here for now.